<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the late seidge and taking of the city of Babylon by the Turke. As it was written from thence by Zarain Aga, one of his captaines, to Caymaran (his brother) vice-roy in Constantinople. Setting forth all the principall passages of this siedge; with one unparreled [sic], cruell, furious and bloody assault, made by the Turks, wherein were slaine in 12 houres. 130000 of them, and above 20000 Persians. Translated out of the Turkish, into the Italian language by the drugerman to the state of Ragouza. And Englished by W.H.</title>
            <author>Zarain, Aga.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120611</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855806</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855806</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21309</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15862)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21309)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1056:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the late seidge and taking of the city of Babylon by the Turke. As it was written from thence by Zarain Aga, one of his captaines, to Caymaran (his brother) vice-roy in Constantinople. Setting forth all the principall passages of this siedge; with one unparreled [sic], cruell, furious and bloody assault, made by the Turks, wherein were slaine in 12 houres. 130000 of them, and above 20000 Persians. Translated out of the Turkish, into the Italian language by the drugerman to the state of Ragouza. And Englished by W.H.</title>
                  <author>Zarain, Aga.</author>
                  <author>Holloway, William, of Ragusa.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Raworth, for N. Butter, and N. Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.H. = William Holloway, whose name appears at end of "The coppy of a letter sent to a private merchant of London", E4r.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank. Variant 1: first leaf bears half-title and woodcut on recto.</note>
                  <note>C1r last line has "our most Potent". Variant 2: C1r last line has "our Omni Potent".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baghdad (Iraq) --  History --  Siege, 1639-1639 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Murad IV, 1623-1640 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21309:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21309:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF THE Late Seidge and taking of the City OF BABYLON BY THE TURKE.</p>
            <p>As it was written from thence by <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Aga,</hi> one of his Captaines, to <hi>Caymaran</hi> (his Brother) Vice-Roy in <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Setting forth all the principall paſſages of this Siedge; With one Unparreled, Cruell, Furious and Bloody aſſault, made by the Turks, wherein were ſlaine in 12 houres. 130000 of them, and above 20000 Perſians.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Turkiſh, into the Italian Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage by the Drugerman to the State of RAGOVZA. And Engliſhed by <hi>W. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. Raworth,</hi> for <hi>N. Butter,</hi> and <hi>N. Bourne.</hi> 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:21309:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21309:2"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION, Deſcribing the City of <hi>Babylon</hi> from its Originall, and how often it hath been tranſlated from one Monarch to another; it being now come againe into the hands of the Turke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not Fortune to which the Romane Orator, as he <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Ad Heren. Fortunam In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanam eſſe &amp; cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam &amp; Brutam perhibent Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophi: Caecam quia nihil cernit quo ſeſe applicet; Inſanam quia in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certa &amp; inſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt; Brutans quia mu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictatur.</note> learnt from the Philoſophers, gives the attributes of Blindneſſe, Madneſſe, and Brutiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; becauſe it ſeeth not whither it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth it ſelfe, is unconſtant and variable, and is encountered by many inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, no humane policy by which the <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ariſtot. <hi>5</hi> polit. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Statiſts of the world would preſcribe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21309:3"/> infallible rules for preſervation of ſetled Kingdomes and Republiques to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but the divine providence which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth the eſtate of things which (admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring, and ruling all things not ſimply alone, but by diſpoſing of the meanes, and ſecondary cauſes) makes that neceſſary by conſequence, which becauſe not foreſeen ſeemeth contingent and fortuitous to the Moale-eyes of blinde mortality.</p>
            <p>Old <hi>Babilon</hi> the metropolis of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> for ſtrength might compare with any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the world; Its firſt Foundreſſe <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramis,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Quem morem veſtis exindegens univerſa te<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t. Ius<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. L. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> A woman of more then maſculine wit and courage, (whoſe Garbe in wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping her head in Lawne the Perſians at this day imitate) firſt ſurrounded it with walls of 32 <note n="(d)" place="margin">Celius A<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lectionum. L. <hi>8.</hi> Cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> foot thicke and 50 Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits high betwixt the Turrets; the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers themſelves being raiſed 10 Cubits higher, And ſo left it as a peece, (in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of that age) impregnable.</p>
            <p>If any City might boaſt of its bigneſſe, this might clayme that glory, It being the <note n="(e)" place="margin">Babiloniaam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſima ſtomni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um urbium orbis cogni<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Iovius Lib <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> biggeſt of the knowne world, And
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21309:3"/> the walls <note n="(f)" place="margin">Celius loc. citato.</note> 355 <note n="(g)" place="margin">A Stadium is <hi>135</hi> paces.</note> Stadia in compaſſe. Or according to <hi>Plinius</hi> his deſcription, <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>c</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The breadth of the walls being 50 foot, the height 200, each foot containing more by 3 fingers breadth then our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meaſure, And in Circuite LX. M. paces.</p>
            <p>To omit that conjecture of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Polit.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> thought it might have an equall dimenſion with all Peloponeſſes, becauſe when it was firſt taken, the fartheſt part of the City knew not till 3 dayes after what had happened: If any City might brag of its Elegancy and commodious ſituation, it was this; <hi>Euphrates</hi> bringing his Channell of a ſtadium broad through the midſt of it, <note n="(k)" place="margin">Cel. L. Citato Curtius et alij.</note> and that ſo arched o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and adorned with penſill Gardens, that afarre off, it appeared like a Wood upon the top of a Mountaine: and the land about being ſo fruitfull, that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly produceth 200 for one, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times 300: <note n="(l)" place="margin">Herod. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> If any City might glory in the happy and pregnant wits of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, it was this, where Aſtronomy
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21309:4"/> was firſt taught, and the Arte of working in needle workes of divers Colours was firſt invented. If ever City might glory in the puiſſance of its Kings, this was that City, wherin the Scepter was firſt ſway'd by <hi>Phulbelochus, Anno mundi</hi> 3146. under whom flouriſhed the Perſian Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher. <hi>Metaſthenes</hi> who reigned 48. yeeres. Next by <hi>Phylazzer</hi> or <hi>Tegbath Phylazzer, Anno mundi</hi> 3194. and reigned 23. yeeres. After him by <hi>Salmanazar, Anno mundi</hi> 3217. who reigned 10. yeers and ſubdued all <hi>Phaenicia, Tyrus</hi> only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and carryed away the King of Iſraell and the 10. Tribes into <hi>Media.</hi> Next by <hi>Sennacherib, Anno mundi</hi> 3227. who reviling the good pious <hi>Hezekiah</hi> by a rayling <hi>Rabſhekeh</hi> had a hooke put into his Noſtrils, forced home againe, and was ſlaine Adoring his Idols in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by his owne Sonnes, when he had reigned 7 yeeres. After him by <hi>Eſarhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> (called by Joſephus <hi>Aſarocoldus, Anno mundi</hi> 3233. who raigned 11 yeares: And laſtly by <hi>Berodach,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Ballad.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21309:4"/> Anno mundi</hi> 3242. who at the revolution of 12. yeares, transferred the Kingdome to the Aſſyrians, and afterwards reigned 18. yeares, yet the ſtrength of its walles, numerous &amp; ingenious inhabitants, and the puiſſance of its Kings could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it in its former ſplendour, it being forced to change the ancient government, and receive new Lords and Lawes, firſt by <hi>Cyrus</hi> the Perſian, and after by <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Great, who was poyſoned there by a Quackſalving Mountebanke, <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> by name <hi>(m)</hi> who had ſo cunningly tempered his potion,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Iuſtin. 1.12.</note> that no veſſell of Earth or glaſſe, braſſe or Iron, nor any thing elſe but an horſes hooſe could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it unleſſe it had been mingled with Cold water, which for a time abated the violence, though ſoone after contracting its power, it raged more violently, in which vehicle it was exhibited unto him: Kings have there Fates, and the great Macedon, which would be thought Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall as God, thus by the hand of a baſe Veneficus knew himſelfe to be a man,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21309:5"/> and dyed like one of the ordinary princes, but his limited time was come. One of the Perſian Wiſemen called <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> 
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Plutarch. <hi>in vita</hi> Alexandri.</note> warned him to leave <hi>Babylon</hi> and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the River unto <hi>Byrſia,</hi> and his Counſell he had followed had not <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archus</hi> the Philoſopher met with him and told him that his Predictions were falſe, and alſo uncertaine; adding withall <hi>Si fatis Conſtant ignota mortalibus:</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuſtin.</hi> Loc. Citat.</note> 
               <hi>Si na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura debeantur Imutabillia.</hi> And ſo convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his underſtanding, betrayed him to the treacherous <hi>Aſſaſinace.</hi> The utter ruine of this great City attended the Fate of this great King, for ſoon after his death, it was in part demoliſhed, by the fury of the Perſians, in part ſuffered to periſh, by the negligence of the Grecians: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt exhauſted and unpeopled by <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cael.</hi> L. Citat.</note> 
               <hi>Seleucus,</hi> who to that intent built <hi>Seleucia</hi> within 300 Stadia, that is 44 Engliſh miles thereof; and the Parthians who to the ſame purpoſe built <hi>Cteſiphon</hi> in <hi>Chalonitis (Juxta tertium ab câ Lapidem)</hi> But then failing of their deſigne, <hi>Vologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21309:5"/> the King (<hi>nuper</hi> ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi> 
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 26</note> ſince the Incarnation of our Saviour it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine) built an other City neere it, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Vologeſo-Certa,</hi> and thereby ſo impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed it, that it might have been ſaid of <hi>Babylon</hi> truely (which a Greeke Comick Poet ſpake of <hi>Megalopolis</hi> in <hi>Arcadea,</hi> ſcoffingly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The great City is become a forſaken wilderneſſe.) Thus the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Eaſterne buildings became as an heape, till the yeere of Chriſt 578. when it was rebuilt by the <hi>Caliph Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giapher,</hi> with the expence of 200000. talents of Gold, and called <hi>Bagdat;</hi> yet that ſplendor was ſoone Eclipſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, by <hi>Alacho,</hi> brother to <hi>Chyta</hi> the Tartarian king <hi>Anno</hi> 640, who expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led The <hi>Abaſian</hi> family <hi>Caliph Muſtiadzen</hi> the 54<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of that houſe then ruling; and the family of <hi>Chita</hi> was againe not long after, beaten out by <hi>Tangrolipix</hi> of the <hi>Zel-Zuccahian</hi> line, whence it deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the houſe of <hi>Ottoman, Anno</hi> 1031 under whom it remained untill the yeere
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21309:6"/> 1625, when it was ſubjected to the <hi>Perſians</hi> by their puiſſant Prince <hi>Abas,</hi> who after 14 yeeres, were forced from it by the now Turkiſh <hi>Sultano,</hi> whoſe proceſſe for the recovery thereof, by the great paines and charge of our Engliſh Relator, is derived to us out of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiva</hi> of <hi>Raguza,</hi> formerly called <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daurus,</hi> a City and Republique in <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia,</hi> but tributary to the grand <hi>Signior,</hi> in the letters following:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21309:6"/>
            <head>The Relation of the late Siege and taking of the City of Babylon, By the <hi>Turke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He deſire you have to know of the true Succeſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of our whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, incited me to write 3. former letters. In my firſt I related unto you what occurents hapned in our voyage, particularly of that moſt <note n="(1)" place="margin">This Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Commander would uſurpe both the Name and Office of our Saviour, &amp; is therfore juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſtyled the <hi>Turke</hi> baſe and wicked.</note> falſe and wicked man who intitling himſelfe Jeſus the great Prophet, was (not very farre from <hi>Babilon</hi>) ſo audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hardy as to joyne Battle with the Invincible Army of the Arbiter of the whole univerſe <note n="(2)" place="margin">Here is baſe flattery and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, the <hi>Turks</hi> parraſit<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, thus entitle him and he aſumes it.</note> the moſt mighty Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror Sultan <hi>Amurath,</hi> the right hand of the Omnipotent God, and how the ſaid bloudy fights ended by the death of the ſaid falſe Prophet and all his Army. <note place="margin">Diſcito juſtitiam moniti nec tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Ieſum.</note> (3)</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21309:7"/>
            <p>In my ſecond, I wrote you how that approaching neere the wals of great <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi> we were aſſaulted by the Army of <hi>Han</hi> Lord of <hi>Perſia:</hi> and how dreadfull the Battaile was: as alſo how a great part of our Army then periſhed: and how the aſpect of the awefull countenance of our moſt majeſticall Emperor, at leaſt forced the Enemy to retire, one part of his Army flying into places farre off, and the other part ſeeking refuge within the wals of <hi>Babilon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my third, I ſignified unto you, that the <hi>Babilonians</hi> hearts fayled them at our approach; when they beheld the vaſte and great Channell and Trenches made by our Army, to divert the river Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes annother way; the great paines of our ſupreame Lord, the admirable diligence of <hi>Huſſaim</hi> Baſſaw; the incomparable vertue of <hi>Mahomet</hi> Baſſaw; the couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vallour of <hi>Mustapha</hi> Baſſaw, and the generall and cordiall fidelity of the whol<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Imperiall Army, all which preſaged the following Victory; as alſo of the foure
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21309:7"/> Batteries planted, in each of which were 50. Peeces of Ordnance, in all 200 pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherewith we continually battered the great <hi>Babilon,</hi> without giving the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies any leave to take the leaſt reſpit: As alſo of the great Aſſault and Trenches made againſt the ſtrong Caſtle of Venlo, by the Noble favorite of our Emperour <hi>Silixtar</hi> Baſſaw; there I alſo wrote unto you how wee then numbred our Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and how many wee found wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, namely: the number of ſuch as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the fore named Battels, in the rayſing of the 4 Baſtions, and in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, amounted to 73,589 light Horſe, with their Riders, amongſt whom the old <hi>Dants</hi> Baſſaw ſanctified by our holy faith, who appeared alwayes like thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and lighting to the Enemies terror: <note n="(4)" place="margin">That is, were ſlaine; the <hi>Turks</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them as Saints &amp; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs which dye by Warre in their Princes ſervice.</note> with many other Lords and great Captaines of the Countreies of <hi>Greece, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bania</hi> and <hi>Morea,</hi> which wee hope that, (like ſo many Cherubins) the chiefeſt of the Angels have conducted their ſoules to Heaven, into the Bozome of <hi>Mahomet</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21309:8"/> our Prophet, whom the great God hath ſo waſhed with the water of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſuffred by them for their faiths ſake.</p>
            <p>There were loſt alſo in the ſame acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 35000 footmen, in part <hi>Janiſſaries,</hi> and in part a new ſort of Souldiers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Simeani;</hi> amongſt whom was <hi>Beleaver Bostanga</hi> Baſſaw, who that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame day on which he was preferred to the dignity of Baſſaw, before he could enjoy terreſtriall Rule, conducted to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven theſe his Souldiers, being drawne to enjoy thoſe Celeſtiall waters, the which GOD hath granted to the Faithfull, through the interceſſion of our great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <note n="(5)" place="margin">
                  <p>There is no cheate like that which cloaths it ſelfe in the habit of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>This the Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Mahomet</hi> promiſed Azoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra 2, and is it this day by them firmely beloved.</p>
               </note> After which, I alſo adviſed you how that the great Ingeneere of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frique had cauſed more than 1000 Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques to be built: And how that 25 Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of unmeaſurable greatneſſe, were laid upon skins blowne full of wind like bladders, and ſo were ſupported, and ſwame on the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> but to what end no one knew.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21309:8"/>
            <p>I further advized you of the great prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and toyle in making the great frame for the Bridge ouer the River, and how that the ſaid River being diverted another way, we preſented the aforeſaid Cannons before the ſtrong walls of Babylon, and then layd the Bridge, at one inſtant fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with ſtrong and long barres of Iron, that upheld it in all thoſe places, which are held neceſſary, and how our deſignes tooke effect and a great part of the walle of Babylon by unceſſant Battery was broke downe, and how the ſaid Artillery toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an Infinit number of our men the diverted River by force, returning ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly into its Antient Channell were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away thereby. And not onely ſo, but that the River alſo broake into the Citty of Babylon, through the breaches in the wall, which our Emperour perceiving, commanded the aforeſaid Barques, full of Souldiers to row into the City, (6) as you have had in my former large information.</p>
            <p>After this there came a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from our Omni Potent Emperour,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21309:9"/> the bridge being finiſhed) that we ſhould fill up the trenches by us made:<note place="margin">It was a ſtrange command and dangerou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: but (<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> piet <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iura regn<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nai cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditas, The Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious to enlarge his Dominions, th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to preſerue his men, and careth not for loſſe of the laſt, ſo he may gaine the firſt.</note> and that about the diſtance of a mile from Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, we ſhould begin a great trench of the length of a mile, in a direct line, but about, miles in its wandring turnings and windings &amp; ſo larg that 30 men in file might commodiouſly march forward therein. This done, the whole Army was divided into foure ſeverall Squadrons, one of them being appointed to each of the aboveſaid 4 baſtions. The leading of the firſt Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron was given to the great <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>izier,</hi> by the Emperour called <hi>Alla,</hi> which in Turkiſh is as much as to ſay, God and Father. The ſecond Commander was the moſt valiant <hi>Muſtapha Baſſawe.</hi> The Conductor of the the third, was the moſt vertuous <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi> The fourth chiefe leader was (the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract and quinteſſence of all honour and vertue) his ſacred Majeſty, the great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour himſelfe, who was contented ſo to doe, contrary to the advice of his chiefe Counſellors, and of all the three Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according to the directions of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneere
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21309:9"/> of <hi>Affrique,</hi> into whoſe hands the Invincible Majeſty of our Emperour had given all his power and authority, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty himſelfe, in this deſigne, contenting to bee commanded by his owne ſlave.</p>
            <p>Over the fifth part of the hoaſt, the great Solicitor had Command, and hee remained to guard thoſe borders, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was reported the (7) unbeleiving Perſian was retired with the reſidue of his forces.<note place="margin">Yet he is a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; what ever is pretended it is not reli<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion but deſire of Rule that makes the quarrell betweene the Turke and him.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After this manner, having put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in order of battaile, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the great Legiſlator, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was given that in every ſeverall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, the moſt eloquent man amongſt them choſen, ſhould by a Marſhall ſpeech animate the Souldiers to fight reſolutely uſing theſe or the like words.</p>
            <p>Moſt valiant Champions, moſt happy ſlaves of the Emperours Majeſty,<note place="margin">Here is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in the ad<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect. Slavery is no happineſſe, and Turkiſh ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vervis the worſt of miſeries, but ſuch as never k<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> liberty take it for a bleſſi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this is the day which you ſo long deſired, this is the end for which you have undergone ſo many miſeries; this is the day that our Empire ſhall bee eſtabliſhed to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21309:10"/> faithfull of God, and fatall to ſuch as believe not the law of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> at which words their courages were doubled, and every one unanimouſly, like ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Lions, were diſpoſed and deſirous in that very inſtant to dye, or elſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Sepulture of our Prophet, IMAN ASEN, which is in the City of Babylon, to the end, that it might not remaine in the hands of misbelievers. And being thus reſolved, wee then mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forwards on the Bridge, which we before had made, being alſo greatly ſpurd on by hearing the terrible confuſed noyſe of thoſe our men, who were as aforeſaid entred into Babylon in barques. So ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily Trumpets and Drummes ſounding, we paſſed over the Bridge, And a deepe large Ditch, and even under the wals, almoſt hand to hand, began a moſt fierce aſſault, in which time it was the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of GOD, that the River of <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> upon that ſide of the City, where the Bridge was built, was on the ſuddaine almoſt quite dryed up, and did take its
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21309:10"/> courſe on the other ſide, the which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by us perceived, Commandement was given, that with great quantity of Sacks of Flaxe, and Sacks of Wooll, Earth, dead bodies of men, and beaſts and ſuch like <note n="(9)" place="margin">What Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſme it is to account the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed men no better then Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh.</note> Rubbiſh, throwne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid dryed channell, by multitudes of men in ſhort time, we made it plainely equall with the other ground, for the ſpace of two miles in length, even under the very wals of the city: the moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Ianiſaries and Simeenis, ſtormed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the city with continuall tempeſts of Musquet ſhot, and gave not the enemy leave to come in ſight, whilſt thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forces which were brought up through the meandrous trench aforeſaid, ſwiftly ran with ſcaling Ladders, each of them being then armed with two Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, and a ſhort crooked ſword hanging by their ſides, called Semitars in this ſort they attempted to ſcale the walls, and to aſcend, but the defendants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, not ſleeping a whit, with hot mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Pitch, and Tarre, Roſen, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21309:11"/> and multitude of ſtones overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us, and with certaine Artillery, ſo monſtrous bigge, that in one of their mouthes a man might commodiouſly lye, theſe being charged with chaines, and nayles, bullets and Iron barres, &amp;c. Swept our men away, wee on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſide, attempting with good Canon, to beat downe their walls to the ground, which at laſt likewiſe tooke effect; but this advantage was accompanied with a greater difficulty, for the defendants had fortified within, and built another very ſtrong brick-wall, neere the which they had made a very deepe and large ditch, all covered over with boards, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a trappe doore, or draw bridge, which they kept levell, untill there had entred into the City about 2000 Ianiſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and perceiving the light horſe to enter alſo, they let fall the trappe doore to our great perill and dammage, for ſuch was the fury of our holy inſpired
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21309:11"/> ſouldiers, to preſſe forwards the ſooner and more effectually to ſhew their man hood and valour, that the hindemoſt forced the formoſt to fall downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into the aforeſaid deepe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Ditch, inſomuch that in a ſhort time, what with our men, and with our Horſes, the Ditch was then filled, And leuelled with the ground. The Defendants ſaw it, and began againe to diſtribute theire ſhott and to thunder with the aboue ſaid widemouth petards, But wee being arrived even vnder the ſaid wall, and as it were at hand blowes, our multitudes at the laſt overcame all their oppoſitions, and forced them to retire to the other ſide of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, leaving theſe battered walls to our diſcretion, upon which wee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played our Emperours moſt happy banners, and they likewiſe on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide did diſplay thoſe of PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIA.</p>
            <p>Thus wee gained the one halfe of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21309:12"/> the City in the ſpace of twelve houres, or thereabouts. The Defendants in this Aſſault having loſt above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand men, and wee on our ſide 130000, amongſt whom the great Vizier was eterniſed by his glorious death, who after he had with incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible vallor, vndanted Courage that ſelfe ſame day, caſt eighty ſeuerall darts againſt the Enemy, was at laſt by a uſquet ſhot ſmote into the forehead, whoſe death our army ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of, called thrice vnitedly, vpon the name of GOD <note n="(10)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nulla <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ens tam fera nemo hominum eſt tam Immanis cuius meatem non imbu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rit Dei Opinio. Cic. Tuſ. Quaeſt.</hi> All men know that there is a God, but not how to ſerve him, ſuperſtition is of a larger growth then Atheiſme.</note> and did alſo moſt humbly recommend his Soule to his Deities acceptance with fervent and hearty Prayers, &amp;c. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner wee having at laſt overcome the Defendants, did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reſt the Lords and Maſters of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21309:12"/> one halfe of the City, whereupon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Camp for that day repoſed; &amp; the very next morning, the Emperor ſent for his moſt faithfull <hi>Muſtapha Baſbaw</hi> to come unto his preſence (who was called <hi>Silix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> which is as much to ſay girt-Sword) hee accordingly preſenting himſelfe, firſt cauſed him to bee arrayed with three ſeverall rich Garments, and with his owne hands girt his Sword about him, and then aſſigned to him his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, ſaying, unto him: Take into thy cuſtody my right hand the Privic Seale and ſhew thy ſelf my valiant (a) Wolfe,<note place="margin">Conveneunt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Nomina, <hi>The Wol<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, ie</hi> Annimal fero<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non generoſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> rapax nunquam turatum.</note> let me ſee how thou wilt behave thy ſelfe in guiding of mine Army in the remainder of the victory. The great Baſhaw (without the leaſt anſwer ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting himſelf downe upon the ground) moſt humbly kiſſed the Emperours hand, and preſently with much haſt tooke horſe, gallopping amaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that part of the City which was by us already overcome, where ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21309:13"/> from his horſe he was received of all the Army with great tryumph. The almighty God the recompencer of our true valour which overcommeth all oppoſitions, infuſed into all our Camp unſpeakable jollity, proſperity, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed us with abundance of all things neceſſary for life, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Numerus Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narius turcis Saceritidem &amp; decimus.</note>Now the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day (b) ſince our firſt arrivall under the ſaid City which was <hi>Friday</hi> neerely approaching; all the chiefe Commanders of the Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to put all things in a readineſſe, being reſolved on the next morning to give the laſt aſſault unto the remainder of the City (yet being in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Babilonians,</hi> and in which was the Caſtle <hi>Venlo</hi>) being one halfe of the whole, well fortified, with about 16000 Defendants, vvho ſeeing hovv things paſſed, amounted their Artillery, ſome part to the left ſide of the City, and the other part to defend the Walls without, on that ſide which out-faced the Battery
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21309:13"/> of the great Baſhaw. Thus being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and all things in order, they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended our comming with great accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, loude noiſes and ſounds of warlike Inſtruments, ſhewing more courage then ever they did before, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But the Reader hath by the way to underſtand that before the comming of the <hi>Turkes</hi> under <hi>Babylon.</hi> The <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had ſent away all unprofitable and unſerviceable perſons (as old Men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children) unto other retired Cities and ſtrong holds of <hi>Perſia,</hi> there being left for guard of the City onely 40000 able garriſon Souldiers, over which were foure principall Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; namely the firſt and chiefeſt was called <hi>Obet Han,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Mentiſen E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> the third <hi>Aſmaean,</hi> and the fourth <hi>Sacker.</hi> Now it happened that the three aforeſaid laſt named Commanders by certaine paſſages had ſome ſuſpition that their chiefe Generall <hi>Obet Han</hi> was corrupted by the great <hi>Turke,</hi> and held private correſpondency with him;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21309:14"/> whereupon with an unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they impriſoned the ſame <hi>Obet Han</hi> in a Tombe, but he ſoone after clearing himſelfe was againe ſet at liberty.</p>
            <p>This night all the aforeſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders called a Councell, wherein af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much conference being propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what medicine was beſt to cure ſo deſperate a diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>The opinion of the ſaid <hi>Obet Han</hi> was, to deliver up the remainder of the City upon any indifferent tearmes. But the other three chiefe Captaines were ſo farre from conſenting thereto, that they plainly told him, if he would not hold out, even unto the laſt man, all the <hi>Perſians</hi> in the City would riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and cauſe him moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diſgracefully to looſe his life.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he (knowing, that they jeſted not, and fearing ſo great a ſtorme would enſue) at midnight gave a ſecret ſigne to our Camp, that he would yeeld and give himſelfe into the pious hands
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21309:14"/> of our Emperour, which he according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did, the great <hi>Turke</hi> promiſing him gracious entertainment <note n="(a)" place="margin">A valiant man cannot bee a Traytor, but Cowardice and Treaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly walke hand in hand, and ſuch was <hi>Han.</hi>
               </note> upon which ſecurity he feigned to his Countrymen that his deſire was, the next morning to be the firſt which would withſtand the furie of the <hi>Turkes</hi> firſt aſſault; whereupon they (no way dreaming of his intention) commended his forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and incouraged him to behave himſelfe valiantly; ſo betimes the next morning hee iſſued forth of his hold with 3000 Souldiers as if it were to withſtand us, but inſtead thereof hee went ſtraight forwards with the ſaid Souldiers unto the lodging of our great <hi>Vizier,</hi> who with much humanity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him, and adviſed our Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of what had hapned who hearing the proceſſe, cauſed the ſaid <hi>Obet Han</hi> to come before his preſence (who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately preſenting himſelfe) <note place="margin">Here the old Rule is croſſed, <hi>Amo Proditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem proditore ode.</hi>
               </note> our Emperour cloathed him with a plaine red Velvet gowne, lyned with Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and a very rich Pendant, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21309:15"/> his Highneſſe had worne in the front of his Turbant, and alſo a Dagger named <hi>Hangiaw,</hi> and unto all the other 3000 Soldiers which accompanied him hee gave very great pay. So that thoſe which were Heretiques even unto that <note n="(d)" place="margin">Muſt he needs be a <hi>Muſſulman</hi> that is ſubject to the Houſe of <hi>Ottoman? Quis l<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t hoc, &amp; in <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>chinnor non ſolvitur?</hi>
               </note> houre, became beleevers of the moſt happie truth of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> The aforeſaid donatives and preſents were given unto the aforeſaid <hi>Obet Han,</hi> becauſe hee had alwaies underhand kept correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with our Emperour which was (as aforeſaid) almoſt revealed: but the Omnipotent God preſerved him in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to the end his honourable actions by future Writers might be publiſhed in (e) holy paper to the whole World.<note place="margin">It might bee <hi>charta Sacra</hi> and ſo paſſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After which we heard in the <hi>Perſians</hi> fortifications a great tumult and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and in that inſtant, certaine of the Defendants deſired a Parley, the which being by us perceived, ſome were ſent to know their minds, which being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, they returned &amp; opened it to the Emperour and his Councell, who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21309:15"/> concluded that the following day there ſhould be on both ſides a ceſſation from Armes, and likewiſe ordered that the following night, at the darke Poſterne doore of the Caſtle all the <hi>Perſian</hi> Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers upon agreement ſhould iſſue foorth with as much Baggage as they vvould carry, and keepe their vvay through the ordinary ſtreet towards <hi>Perſia.</hi> And to this end order was given, that the Camp of <hi>Silixtar</hi> great Baſhaw ſhould make them way and retire from theſe Fronti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but there aroſe a ſuſpition, &amp; it vvas the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon bruit amongſt our Soldiers that the <hi>Perſians</hi> fled, and that in a tuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner without rendring the leaſt Obedience to our army (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded thereunto one vvhile by admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, another vvhile by menaces) w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> this their intollerable obſtinacy cauſed our men to ruſh all in an Impetous fury tovvards thoſe parts, where the <hi>Perſians</hi> vvere, vvho knowing full well in vvhat deſperate caſe they were (Death threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them on all ſides) prepared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21309:16"/> for their beſt defence, vvhich pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration cauſed a rumour, &amp; the rumor ſo affrighted the <hi>Turks</hi> which were Iod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in that part of the City already won, (fearing ſome great ayd was come from the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> to ſuccour the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Babilonians</hi>) that thereupon they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke all the holds they had before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and fled. Inſomuch, that had not the Captaines of the <hi>Ianizaries</hi> aſſured them of the truth, and incouraged them immediatly to returne (all that was got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with ſo great an effuſion of guiltleſſe blood) had been all in a trice loſt again.</p>
            <p>In this bloody Fight was a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſlaughter on both ſides, and a mortall deſtruction fell upon all thoſe <hi>Perſians</hi> which (as aforeſaid) had iſſued foorth, the moſt part of them were ſlaine (the ground drinking in their Hereticall blood with the blood of many holy Imperials; inſomuch, that but 300 of our Enemies eſcaped death that day) who (being taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners alive) and ſaid that the faithleſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21309:16"/> Promiſe of our Emperour had deceived them; But wee anſwered them that though our Emperor had given them his faith, not to moleſt them in their paſſage, yet this his pleaſure was not proclaimed through the Campe, therefore we were not bound to obſerve it: where upon, preſently after they were brought to a place neere the <hi>Dudiglien</hi> or Tent of the great Vizier, and were all beheaded. This tragedy being ſeen by the <hi>Perſians,</hi> which kept the Caſtle, made them prepare for their defence, unto whom our Emperor ingaged his faith and promiſed them to proclaime it through the whole Campe, according to their own hearts deſire; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, they remayned obſtinate: and notwithſtanding, that all day long they were perſwaded to accept thereof, they would not conſent thereto, for which cauſe there came out a Comaund, that the next day following, both in the Ditches, and without, a generall aſſault ſhould be made, which was accordingly performed; and wee approaching to the outward
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21309:17"/> ditch of the Caſtle, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was a pike long in depth, and another in breadth, which hindred our entrance into a broader green; we indeavoured with a great quantity of beames and timber to fill up the ditches, and, as it were, to make a kind of a Bridg, wherby our deſigne might take effect. But whilſt we were thus ſeriouſly imployed about this work, the defendants from the out wals of the Caſtle with their musket ſhot, and from their Baſtions with their Artillery, made great havock of our men; yet nevertheleſſe, in the ſpace of an houre we had laid our beames, and made a kind of Bridge, by the which our Souldiers thronged over to the aforeſaid greene, where being come, wee found another Ditch halfe as deep, and as broad as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thorow which paſſed a river, and whilſt ſome of our men earneſtly attended with their musket ſhot, not giving leave to the defendants once to ſhew themſelvs upon the wals of the Caſtle, others of our renowned beſt Souldiers, by their ſcaling Ladders mounted up the walles, a mine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21309:17"/> was ſprung, the violence whereof not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blew up all thoſe which had paſſed the aforeſaid bridg, but alſo the very bridg it ſelfe, and not only ſo, but as it happened, this mine fired another mine, which was under the ſecond ditch and wall, which unſuſpectedly taking fire, blew up many of the defendants, who were on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wals, and the ſtones of the ſaid 2 mines, alſo greatly damnified all thoſe of our Camp, which were in the 3 quarter-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered-City, and as many as were neere thereunto; being one of the moſt horrible and dreadfull ſights vvhich hath beene ſeene by any mortall, ſince the Creation. This miſerable accident being over, thoſe of our men (vvhich vvere left alive, tooke quiet poſſeſſion of the doores of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle firſt, and aftervvard, by plaine force, of the Caſtle it ſelfe, there remaining in it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live only 300 <hi>Perſians,</hi> and thoſe unarm'd, and vvithout any thing left vvherevvith to defend themſelves (ſave that each of them had a ſhort crooked ſvvord by their ſides, called Simytars) their povvder and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21309:18"/> all their materials for defence, being ſpent, ſtood upon their guard and fought ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperatly, that in the terrible conflict, many of our Juſt Imperials loſt their lives: But at laſt our multitudes overcame them, and put them all to the ſword. Thus after the above ſaid maner, the great deſtroy'd <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> became wholy ours. But as the valor expreſſed by our Souldiers, is beyond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, ſo was alſo the courage of the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, which will adde unto us an eternal fame, ſo ſtrong a Fortreſſe being never heretofore taken by force, neither ever any Souldiers more obedient to their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours than ours were; neither ever any Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, King, or Potentate from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo liberall in gifts, as this our God of the Earth was.</p>
            <p>I (thanks be to God) remaine yet alive, but wounded by a Musket ſhot in the thigh, when wee became maſters of the Caſtle doore, and thus wounded, I write this relation unto you, being untill this preſent day, in the behalfe, &amp; by direction and order from our terreſtiall God; daily
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21309:18"/> viſited by <hi>Selictar</hi> Baſſaw, whereby, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the wound, greatly mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth me, yet I have comfort and heartely rejoyce, that my body is marked for the holy faiths ſake, and I ſhall not too much emulate, the felicity of our dead: ſince that the pious God knew well the ambition I had to dye in defence of our moſt holy faith, and in ſervice of my Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, who ſo often ſhews ſuch evident ſignes of his affection towards me, as I my ſelfe could neither expect or deſire; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my longing is to meet with an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, whereby I may give a teſtimonie, that, after God, he is my ſoule. As for the reſt, there remaine yet alive unto me foure horſes and 3 ſervants (whom God bleſſe &amp; ſend them good fortune) that they may deſerve their ſtipends, and leave fame to their children. As for the victuals for our Camp (by the Providence of God) wee found great ſtore in the City, and alſo by the diligence of our Emperour, wee have great abundance of all things, making continuall feaſts with roaring of Artillery and praying to God for the proſperity &amp;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21309:19"/> happy ſucceſſe of our Almighty Emperor, as you alſo ought by the Emperors com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, to give notice to all his ſubjects that they obſerve the like.</p>
            <p>In this City we found 145 Canons for battery, the which carried ſhot of 50 and 70 pound weight; 92 morter pieces, in the which any man might ſtand moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, but little or no wealth at all, becauſe all before our coming was carried away from thence, nothing remaining but what was neceſſary to maintain the life of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſaid 40000 Souldiers, there left in guarde of the City. There were alſo ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient victuals found to maintaine 40000 ſoules for the ſpace of 2 years: We found alſo 200 Runtars of powder, &amp; the City wholy deſtroy'd, which we are about to refortifie. If any other matter of moment ſhall happen, I will exactly informe you. Thus praying that whatſoever you deſire may be fulfilled, in as much as it aymeth to the proſperity of our Emperor and his Crown, Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Camp.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21309:19"/>
            <head>The Coppy of a letter ſent to a private Merchant of London, from Ragouza.</head>
            <p>THis foreſaid Relation is here of all held for a certaine truth, this State having ſent the ſelfe ſame news to the Pope and Vice-Roy of Naples, and to many other Christian Princes, and hath alſo beene confirmed to bee true, by a <hi>100</hi> ſeverall Carryers, wherefore be pleaſed to make much thereof, aſſuring you if you knew how I laboured to get out the Coppy of the Originall, out of the private News booke of this State, kept in the hands of their chief Secretary, you would questionleſse esteeme it ſo much the more: My paines in tranſlating it (though not ſmall) yet far leſſe than the procuring of the Originall by which above ſaid diſcription, I take notice of <hi>3</hi> points, <hi>viz. 1,</hi> of the proud blaſphemy of the great Turk, in Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuling himſelf the right hand of God, Arbiter of the Vniverſe, and God on Earth. <hi>2,</hi> Of their fooliſh ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions and idle opinions, to beleeve that all thoſe their Souldiers that dye in fight must neceſſarily thereby gaine Heaven. <hi>3,</hi> Of their bestiall precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated reſolution and vaine glory of the great Turk, that ſo hee may gaine and accompliſh his ambitious deſires, regards not to ſee before his face the Bucher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſlaughter of multitudes of his men, and braveſt Souldiers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Read this Relation to as many as your diſcretion thinkes fit, but I deſire you to let no Coppy bee taken thereof, that it may not on the ſuddaine become common: And thus I humbly rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obed: Ser: to command. WIL: HOLLOWAY.</signed>
            </closer>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21309:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:21309:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
